Douglas C. Wu

https://wckdouglas.github.io wckdouglas@gmail.com | 310.658.1540

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Highly-motivated fast learner with > 5 years of quantitative and computational research experiences in next-generation sequencing method developments. Collaborative and innovative with strong communication and interpersonal abilities. Staying up-to-date with industrial trends in sequencing and programming technologies. Comfortable with working in a fast-paced environment.

EDUCATION

UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN

PHD, SPECIALIZED IN BIOINFORMATICS 2013 - 2019 | Austin, TX Advisor: Alan M. Lambowitz University Graduate Continuing Fellowships (2017-2018)

UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS AT URBANA CHAMPAIGN

BS IN BIOCHEMISTRY
May 2013 | Champaign, IL
Biochemistry High Distinction Award
Dean List (Fall 2010, Spring 2011)

LINKS

Github://wckdouglas LinkedIn://wckdouglas Twitter://@wckdouglas Google Scholar://Douglas C. Wu

SKILLS

PROGRAMMING

Ordered by proficiency

- Python R Bash
- Matlab Octave ETFX
- C/C++ MySQL
- Experienced with Scikit-learn and SciPy ecosystem
- Deep learning framework: Pytorch, Keras/Tensorflow
- Familiar with -omics databases and their APIs
- High-performance computing

EXPERIMENTAL

• Cell-free

DNA-seg/RNA-seg/bisulfite-seg

- Molecular diagnostics
- Liquid biopsies
- Live cell imaging

OPEN SOURCE PROJECTS

MAINTAINER

- wckdouglas/sequencing_tools (python package)
- wckdouglas/deep_cfNA (python package)

CONTRIBUTOR

- pysam-developers/pysam (python package)
- jdidion/atropos (python package)
- cran/colorspace (R shiny package)

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

METHOD DEVELOPMENTS IN HIGH-THROUGHPUT SEQUENCING | GRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANT Dec 2013 – present | University of Texas at Austin, Austin, TX

- Developed streamlined RNA-seq and ssDNA-seq methods using thermostable group II intron reverse transcriptase
- Developed and deployed large scale simulation and data analytic tools (python and R) to identify biases in genomic data collections
- Built software to extract information from genomic data for training and predicting biologically-relevant signatures in existing genomic datasets
- Devised statistical and quantitative metrics for benchmarking methods in collecting and analyzing terabytes of genomic data
- Developed data pipeline for reproducible data analysis
- Worked with Center for Quantitative Biology to build and manage remote scalable storage server

MECHANOBIOLOGY | RESEARCH ASSISTANT/ROTATION STUDENT

Feb 2011 – Feb 2014 | University of Illinois at Urbana Champaign, Champaign, IL & University of Texas at Austin, Austin, TX

- Designed and deployed computer simulations to quantify magnetic-induced force that directs embryoid bodies into mesodermal lineages
- Identified force-induced biochemical changes in embryonic stem cells and tumorigenic cells with live-cell imaging
- Identified biophysical regulations during the formation of organized germ layers from a single mouse embryonic stem cell

RECENT PUBLICATIONS

- Xu H*, Yao J*, <u>Wu DC</u>* and Lambowitz AM (2018). Improved TGIRT-seq methods for comprehensive transcriptome profiling with decreased adapter dimer formation and bias correction. Scientific Reports. 9:7953 (*contributed equally).
- <u>Wu DC</u>, Yao J, Ho KS, Lambowitz AM and Wilke CO (2018). Limitations of alignment-free tools in total RNA-seq quantification. BMC Genomics. 19:510.
- <u>Wu DC</u> and Lambowitz AM (2017). Facile single-stranded DNA sequencing of human plasma DNA via thermostable group II intron reverse transcriptase template switching. Scientific Reports. 7:8421.